

# **Raihan Khan**

Nationality: Bangladeshi Date of birth: 15/06/1997

Phone number: (+880) 01521331536 Email address: raihankhanraka@gmail.com

O Home: 1236 Dhaka (Bangladesh)

# **ABOUT ME**

As a Golang Backend developer, I have developed and maintained Kubernetes controllers to provision databases on any private and public clouds. My responsibilities extended to designing and implementing CRD based features to simplify and automate routine database tasks. My experience also encompasses building monitoring stack with ELK, secured Docker images for applications, Bash scripts, Customised Grafana Dashboards, along with implementing effective CI/CD pipelines and release workflows.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

**Senior Software Engineer** 

Appscode Ltd. [ 01/08/2023 - Current ]

City: Dhaka

Country: Bangladesh

- Design and implement Kubernetes controllers to provision databases on any private and public clouds
- Provide client support in migrating to product releases and troubleshooting
- Lead the team in implementing new features

#### **Software Engineer**

Appscode Ltd. [ 01/08/2021 - 31/07/2023 ]

City: Dhaka

Country: Bangladesh

- Develop and maintain Kubernetes controllers to provision databases on any private and public clouds
- Implement CRD based solutions to simplify and automate routine database tasks such as Monitoring, Upgrading, Scaling, Volume Expansion, Backup, Recovery, Failure detection, and Reconfiguration.

### **PROJECTS**

### **KubeDB**

[ 01/08/2021 - Current ]

- Designed and developed Kubernetes controllers from scratch to provision and manage Elasticsearch, Kibana, Apache Kafka, Rabbitmq, Opensearch Dashboards along with required kubernetes resources.
- Enhanced database controllers capability by implementing Kubernetes native features like TLS Reconfiguration, Vertical Scaling, Restart, Volume Expansion, Version Upgrade, and Horizontal Scaling for day 2 lifecycle management.
- Improved database management flexibility by developing features including Metrics reporter sidecar, Custom configuration, TLS secure communication, Customizable health checker with continuous read/write monitoring, Vault managed secret etc.
- Provided monitoring support using **Prometheus and customized Grafana Dashboards** to ensure the stability and performance of database clusters on Kubernetes.
- Ensured products reliability by removing CVE from database images, implementing automated testing pipelines Using GitHub actions CI for databases and ensuring default container/pod security configurations.
- Managed the team by planning, designing and guiding in production ready controller development for new databases namely Solr, Druid, Singlestore, and tools like Kafka Connect.
- Provided client support in troubleshooting controller operations, database migration, upgrade etc.
- · Contributed in reaching end users through live webinars on latest features and technical blogs .
- Achieved 335k+ downloads for the main docker image and have subscribed clients who are reselling it to more than 100
   0+ end users.

Link: <a href="https://kubedb.com/">https://kubedb.com/</a>

#### Stash

[ 04/2023 - 05/2023 ]

• Improved user experience by adding support for Pre-calculated storage size for Persistent Volume to temporarily store database snapshot backups before uploading to remote cloud backend repository or restoring to database from it.

Link: https://stash.run/

### **DIGITAL SKILLS**

### **Tools and Technologies**

Kubernetes / Docker / ELK stack ( Elasticsearch, Kibana, Logstash ) / Grafana & Prometheus / Jenkins / Google Kubernetes Engine (GKE) / REST, gRPC / Helm chart / FluentD / Git-GitHub

#### **Databases and Systems**

RabbitMQ / Kafka / OpenSearch / MySQL & MongoDB

### Languages

Backend development (Golang) / Python / Bash Scripts / C++

### **EDUCATION AND TRAINING**

# **Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Engineering**

**Comilla University** [ 2016 – 2021 ]

City: Cumilla

Country: Bangladesh
Website: <a href="https://cou.ac.bd">https://cou.ac.bd</a>

### **PUBLICATIONS**

# Medication correlation analysis for outbreak prediction

[2023]

Bulletin of Electrical Engineering and Informatics (BEEI) · Jan 8, 2023

# **LANGUAGE SKILLS**

Mother tongue(s): Bangla

### Other language(s):

### **English**

LISTENING C2 READING B2 WRITING B2

SPOKEN PRODUCTION C1 SPOKEN INTERACTION C1

Levels: A1 and A2: Basic user; B1 and B2: Independent user; C1 and C2: Proficient user

# **ACHIEVEMENTS**

# **Competitive Programming**

Participated in 15 national level programming contests including **ICPC Dhaka Regional Contest 2019** (as CoU Dauntless) and **National Collegiate Programming Contest 2018 and 2020** (as CoU Mirror Squad)